<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The substance of that vvhich was deliuered in a sermon before the Commons House of Parliament, in St. Margarets Church at Westminster, the 18. of February, 1620. By Iames Vssher, Professor of Diuinity in the Uniuersity of Dublin, in Ireland</title>
            <author>Ussher, James, 1581-1656.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1621</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 99 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14237</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24553.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118943</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854150</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854150</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19558</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14237)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19558)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1042:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The substance of that vvhich was deliuered in a sermon before the Commons House of Parliament, in St. Margarets Church at Westminster, the 18. of February, 1620. By Iames Vssher, Professor of Diuinity in the Uniuersity of Dublin, in Ireland</title>
                  <author>Ussher, James, 1581-1656.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 50 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Felix Kyngston, for Iohn Bartlet: and are to be sold at the signe of the gilded Cup, in the Goldsmiths Rowe in Cheapside,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1621.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A sermon preached before the Commons House of Parliament.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 24556 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19558:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19558:1"/>
            <p>THE SVBSTANCE OF THAT WHICH WAS DELIVERED IN A SER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon before the Commons Houſe of <hi>Parliament, in</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. MARGARETS Church at Weſtminſter, the 18, of February, 1620.</p>
            <p>By IAMES VSSHER, PROFES<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SOR OF DIVINITY IN THE Vniuerſity of DVELIN, <hi>in Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Imprinted at London by <hi>Felix Kyngston,</hi> for <hi>Iohn Bartlet:</hi> and are to be ſold at the ſigne of the gilded Cup, in the Goldſmiths Rowe in Cheapſide. 1621.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19558:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19558:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOVRABLE ASSEMBLY of the Commons Houſe of Parliament.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T pleaſed this Honourable Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to require my ſeruice, in prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching at that late religious meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of yours, for the receiuing of the holy Sacrament of the Lords Supper. I was afterward alſo ſent vnto by the like authority, to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh that which (according to my poore ability) I then deliuered. And although in reſpect of my ſelfe, and of my want of time to proſecute ſuch a ſubiect, I could wiſh I had beene ſpared from ſuch a taske: yet rather then the expectation, and expreſſe ſignification of the deſire of the repreſentatiue body of the whole Commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty of the Kingdome ſhould rest vnſatisfied; I haue yeelded to commit this vnto the diſpoſing and directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of them, for whoſe ſakes it was at firſt vndertaken. <hi>Opprimi enim me onere officij malui, quàm id,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cic.</note> 
               <hi>quod mihi cum fide ſemel impoſitum fuit, prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter infirmitatem animi deponere.</hi> The very words which then I vttered, I am not able to preſent vnto you: the ſubſtance of the matter I haue truly laid downe,
<pb facs="tcp:19558:3"/>though in ſome places (as it fell out) ſomewhat con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted, in others a little more inlarged. Whatſoeuer it is, I wholly ſubmit it vnto your graue cenſures: and ſo beſeeching the Lord to giue you proſperous ſucceſſe in all your worthy indeuours for the ſeruice of God, his Maieſty and your Countrey, I rest</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in all Chriſtian duty to be commanded, IAMES VSSHER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19558:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1. COR. 10. Verſ. 17.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Wee being many, are one bread, and one body: for we are all partakers of that one bread.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Ther entrance I need not make vnto my ſpeech at this time, then that which the Apoſtle himſelfe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenteth vnto mee in the verſe next but one going before my Text: <hi>I ſpeake to wiſe men.</hi> The more <hi>vnwiſe</hi> might I deeme my ſelfe to be, who being ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcious vnto my ſelfe of my great weakeneſſe, durſt aduenture to diſcouer the ſame before ſo graue and iudicious an Auditory; but that this conſideration doth ſomewhat ſupport me, that no great blame can light herein vpon mee, but ſome aſperſion thereof muſt reflect vpon your ſelues, who happened to make ſo euill a choyce; the more facile I expect you to bee in a cauſe, wherein you your ſelues are ſome wayes intere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:19558:4"/>
            <p> The ſpeciall cauſe of your aſſembling at this time, is, firſt, that you who profeſſe the ſame truth, may ioyne in one body, and partake together of the ſame bleſſed Communion: and then, that ſuch as adhere vnto falſe worſhip, may bee diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered and auoyded: You in your wiſedome diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this holy Sacrament to bee, as it were, <hi>ignis probationis,</hi> which would both <hi>congregare ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mogenea,</hi> and <hi>ſegregare heterogenea,</hi> (as in Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophie wee vſe to ſpeake) both conioyne thoſe that be of the ſame, and diſ-ioyne ſuch as bee of a differing kinde and diſpoſition. And to this purpoſe haue I made choyce of this preſent Text: wherein the Apoſtle maketh our partaking of the Lords Table to bee a teſtimony, not onely of the vnion and communion which wee haue betwixt our ſelues, and with our Head, (which he doth in the expreſſe words, which I haue read) but alſo of our diſ-vnion and ſeparation from all idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous worſhip: as appeareth by the application hereof vnto his maine drift and intendment, laid downe in the 14. and 21. verſes.</p>
            <p>The effect therfore of that which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in expreſſe termes heere deliuereth, is the <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Saints:</hi> which conſiſteth of two parts; the fellowſhip which they haue with the <hi>Body,</hi> laid downe in the beginning; and the fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip which they haue with the <hi>Head,</hi> laid downe in the end of the verſe: both which are thus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained by Saint <hi>Iohn: That which wee haue ſeene and heard, declare we vnto you, that ye alſo may haue fellowſhip with vs; and truly our fellowſhip is with
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19558:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Father, and with his Sonne Ieſus Christ,</hi> 1. Ioh. 1.3. Let them therefore that walke in darkneſſe, brag as much as they liſt of their good-fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: this bleſſed Apoſtle aſſureth vs, that ſuch onely as doe walke in the light,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 1.6, 7.</note> 
               <hi>haue fellowſhip one with another;</hi> euen as they haue fellowſhip with God, and Ieſus Chriſt his Sonne, whoſe blood ſhall cleanſe them from all ſinne. And to what better company can a man come,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.23, 24.</note> than <hi>to the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Aſſembly, and Church of the firſt-borne which are inrolled in heauen, and to God the Iudge of all, and to the ſpirits of iuſt men made perfect, and to Ieſus the Mediator of the new Couenant, and to the blood of ſprinkling, which ſpeaketh better things then that of Abel?</hi> No fellowſhip (doubtleſſe) is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable to this <hi>Communion of Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To begin therefore with the firſt part there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; as the Apoſtle in the third to the Galatians maketh our being <hi>baptized into Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 3.27, 28.</note> to bee a teſtimony that wee <hi>are all one in Chriſt:</hi> ſo doth hee heere make our <hi>partaking of that one bread,</hi> to be an euidence that we alſo are all <hi>one bread, and one body</hi> in him. And to the ſame purpoſe, in the twelfth Chapter following, he propoundeth both our Baptiſme and our drinking of the Lords Cup, as ſeales of the ſpirituall coniunction of vs all into one myſticall body.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 12.12, 13.</note> 
               <hi>For as the body is one,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and hath many members, and all the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of that one body, being many, are one body: ſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo is Christ. For by one Spirit are we all baptized into one body, whether wee bee Iewes or Gentiles, whether we be bond or free: and haue been all made to drinke
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19558:5"/>into one Spirit.</hi> Afterwards hee addeth, that wee <hi>are the body of Christ, and members in particular:</hi> and in another place alſo,<note place="margin">Ibid. verſ. 27.</note> that <hi>We being many, are one body in Christ,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 12.5.</note> 
               <hi>and euery one members one of another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the vſe which hee teacheth vs to make of this wonderfull coniunction (whereby wee are made members of Chriſt, and members one of another) is two-fold: 1. <hi>That there ſhould be no ſchiſme in the body.</hi> 2. <hi>That the members ſhould haue the ſame care one for another,</hi> 1. Cor. 12.25. For preuenting of Schiſme, hee exhorteth vs in the fourth to the Epheſians,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.3-6.</note> 
               <hi>to keepe the vnity of the Spirit in the bond of peace:</hi> and to make this bond the firmer, hee putteth vs in minde of <hi>one Body, one Spirit, one Hope, one Lord, one Faith, one Baptiſme, one God and Father of all, who is aboue all, and through all, and in vs all:</hi> by this multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of vnities declaring vnto vs, that the knots whereby wee are tyed together, are both in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber more, and of farre greater moment, then that matters of ſmaller conſequence ſhould diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuer vs: and therefore that wee ſhould <hi>ſtand fast in one ſpirit, with one minde, ſtriuing together for the faith of the Goſpell, and in nothing terrified by our aduerſaries,</hi> Philip. chap. 1. verſ. 27, 28.</p>
            <p>But howſoeuer God hath thus marſhalled his Church in a goodly order,<note place="margin">Cant. 6.4.</note> 
               <hi>terrible as an army with banners:</hi> yet, ſuch is the diſorder of our nature, that many for all this breake ranke, and the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my laboureth to breed diuiſion in Gods Houſe,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19558:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>that ſo his Kingdome might not ſtand. Nay, often times it commeth to paſſe,<note place="margin">Cant. 5.7.</note> that the <hi>Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> themſelues, who were appoynted for the ſafegarding of the Church, proue in this kinde to bee the ſmiters and wounders of her: and from among them who were purpoſely ordained in the Church, for the bringing of men<note n="*" place="margin">Veteres ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turas ſcrutans, inuenire non poſſum, ſcidiſſe Eccleſiam &amp; de domo Dei popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los ſeduxiſſe, praeter illos qui Sacerdotes à Deo poſiti fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant &amp; Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetae. <hi>Hieron.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>into the vnity of the faith, and of the knowledge of the Son of God,</hi> ouen from among thoſe, ſome doe ariſe, that <hi>ſpeake peruerſe things, to draw away diſciples af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus wee finde in the Eccleſiaſticall Hiſtory,<note n="*" place="margin">Epheſ. 4 13. Act. 20.30.</note> that after the death of <hi>Iulian</hi> the <hi>Apoſtata,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Sozo. men. lib. <hi>6.</hi> hiſt. Eccleſiaſt. cap. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stions and diſputes concerning matters of doctrine were freſhly ſet afoot by thoſe who were ſet ouer the Churches.</hi> Wherupon <hi>Sozomen</hi> maketh this graue obſeruation: that<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>the diſpoſition of men is ſuch, that when they are wronged by others, they are at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement among themſelues; but when they are freed of euils from abroad, then they make inſurrections one against another.</hi> Which as we finde to be too true by the late experience of our neighbour Churches in the Low Countries: ſo are we to conſider with the Wiſe man,<note n="c" place="margin">Eccleſ. 3.15.</note> that <hi>What hath been, is now, and that which is to bee, hath already been:</hi> and bee not ſo inquiſitiue,<note n="d" place="margin">Eccleſ. 6.10.</note> why <hi>the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer dayes were better then theſe? for wee doe not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire wiſely concerning this.</hi> When like troubles were in the Church heretofore, <hi>Iſidorus Pelu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiota,</hi> an ancient Father, moueth the queſtion,<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Jſidor. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſ lib. <hi>4.</hi> epiſt. <hi>133.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>What a man ſhould doe</hi> in this caſe? and maketh anſwere, that <hi>If it be poſsible, wee ſhould mend it,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:19558:6"/>but if that may not bee, wee ſhould hold our peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Apoſtles reſolution, I thinke, may giue ſufficient ſatisfaction in this poynt, to all that haue moderate and peaceable mindes.<note n="f" place="margin">Phil. 3.15, 16.</note> 
               <hi>If in any thing yee bee otherwiſe minded, God ſhall reueale euen this vnto you: neuertheleſſe, whereto wee haue already attained, let vs walke by the ſame rule, let vs minde the ſame thing.</hi> It is not to bee looked for, that all good men ſhould agree in all things: neither is it fit that we ſhould (as our Aduerſaries doe) put the truth vnto compromiſe, and to the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of an <hi>Achitophel,</hi> whoſe counſell muſt bee accepted, <hi>as if a man had inquired at the Oracle of God.</hi> We all agree that the Scriptures of God are the perfect rule of our faith: wee all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in the maine grounds of Religion drawne from thence: wee all ſubſcribe to the articles of doctrine agreed vpon in the Synode of the yeere 1562. <hi>for the auoyding of diuerſities of opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and the eſtabliſhing of conſent touching true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</hi> Hitherto, by Gods mercy, haue wee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready attained; thus farre therefore let vs minde the ſame thing: let not euery wanton wit be permitted to bring what fancies he liſt, into the Pulpit, and to diſturbe things that haue been well ordered.<note place="margin">Rom. 16.17.</note> 
               <hi>I beſeech you, brethren</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>marke them which cauſe diuiſions and offences, contrary to the doctrine which yee haue lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and auoid them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If in ſome other things wee bee otherwiſe minded, than others of our brethren are; let vs beare one with another, vntill God ſhall reueale
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19558:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>the ſame thing vnto vs: and howſoeuer we may ſee cauſe why we ſhould diſſent from others in matter of opinion; yet let vs remember, that that is no cauſe why wee ſhould breake the Kings peace, and make a rent in the Church of God. A thing deepely to be thought of by the <hi>Iſmaels</hi> of our time, whoſe <hi>hand is againſt euery man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 16.12.</note> 
               <hi>and euery mans hand againſt them;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 5.15.</note> who <hi>bite and deuoure one another,</hi> vntill they <hi>bee conſumed one of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;</hi> who forſake the fellowſhip of the Saints, and<note n="*" place="margin">Vos ergo qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ſeparatione ſacrilegâ pacis vinculum diru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtis? <hi>Auguſt. lib. 2. de Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmo contra Donat.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. I ſay and proteſt, that to make ſchiſme in the Church, is no leſſe euill, than to fall into hereſie. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſt. in Epheſ. Hom. 11.</hi>
               </note> by a ſacrilegious <hi>ſeparation</hi> breake this bond of peace. Little doe theſe men conſider, how precious the peace of the Church ought to bee in our eyes (to bee redeemed with a thouſand of our liues) and of what dangerous conſequence the matter of ſchiſme is vnto their owne ſoules. For howſoeuer the ſchiſmaticke <hi>ſecundùm affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum</hi> (as the Schoolemen ſpeake) in his intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and wicked purpoſe, taketh away vnity from the Church; euen as he that hateth God, doth take away goodneſſe from him, as much as in him lyeth: yet <hi>ſecundùm effectum,</hi> in truth and in very deed, hee taketh away the vnity of the Church onely from himſelfe: that is, hee cutteth himſelfe off from being vnited with the reſt of the body; and being diſſeuered from the body, how is it poſſible that he ſhould retaine commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with the Head?</p>
            <p>To conclude therefore this firſt vſe which wee are to make of our communion with the <hi>Body:</hi> let vs call to minde the exhortation of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle: <hi>Aboue all things</hi> put on <hi>loue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 3.14, 15.</note> 
               <hi>which is the bond
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19558:7"/>of perfectneſſe, and let the peace of God rule in your hearts, to the which alſo ye are called in one Body.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold how good and pleaſant a thing it is for bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren to dwell together in vnity:<note place="margin">Pſal. 133.1.</note> what a goodly thing it is to behold ſuch an honourable Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly as this is,<note place="margin">Pſal. 122 3.</note> to bee as a houſe that is <hi>compact to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether</hi> in it ſelfe; holding fit correſpondence with the other part of this great body, and due ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination vnto their and our Head! Such as wiſh not well to the publike good, and would reioyce at the ruine of our State, long for nothing more, then that diſſenſions ſhould ariſe here, betwixt the members mutually, and betwixt them and the Head.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hoc Ithacus velit, &amp; magno mercentur Atridae.</hi> They know full well,<note place="margin">Math. 12.25.</note> that <hi>euery Kingdome diuided againſt it ſelfe, is brought to deſolation; and euery houſe diuided against it ſelfe, ſhall not ſtand:</hi> nor doe they forget the Politicians old rule, <hi>Diuide &amp; impera,</hi> Make a diuiſion, and get the dominion. The more neede haue wee to looke herein vnto our ſelues; who cannot bee ignorant how dolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous <hi>Solutio continui,</hi> and how dangerous <hi>Rup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> proue to bee vnto our bodies. If therefore there be any comfort of loue, if any fellowſhip of the ſpirit,<note place="margin">Phil. 2.1, 2, 3.</note> fulfill our ioy: <hi>that yee be like-min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, hauing the ſame loue, being of one accord, of one minde;</hi> and doing <hi>nothing through ſtrife or vaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glory.</hi> Remember that as oft as we come vnto the Lords Table, ſo oft doe we enter into new bonds of peace, and tye our ſelues with firmer knots of loue together: this bleſſed Communion being a
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19558:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſacred ſeale not onely of the vnion which wee haue with our Head by <hi>faith,</hi> but alſo of our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction with the other members of the body by <hi>loue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereby as we are admoniſhed to maintaine vnity among ourſelues, <hi>that there be no ſchiſme or diuiſion in the body:</hi> ſo are we alſo further put in minde, <hi>that the members ſhould haue the ſame care one for another.</hi> For that is the ſecond vſe which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth vs to make hereof, in 1. Cor. 12.26. which he further amplifieth in the verſe next following, by the mutuall ſympathy and fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-feeling which the members of the ſame bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy haue one with another. For <hi>whether one mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ſuffer, all the members ſuffer with it; or one mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber be honoured, all the members reioyce with it:</hi> and then he addeth: <hi>Now ye are the body of Christ, and members in particular.</hi> Shewing vnto vs thereby, that as wee are all<note n="*" place="margin">Epheſ. 3.6.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporated (as it were) and made copartners of the promiſe in Chriſt: ſo wee ſhould haue one another in our hearts,<note n="*" place="margin">2. Cor. 7.3.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to die and liue together. And hereupon is that exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation in the 13. to the Hebrewes grounded:<note place="margin">Heb. 13.3.</note> 
               <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member them that are in in bonds, as bound with them, and them which ſuffer aduerſity, as being your ſelues alſo in the Body.</hi> It being a perillous ſigne that we be no liuely members of that body, if we be not ſenſible of the calamities that lye vpon our afflicted brethren. We know the <hi>Woe</hi> that is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced againſt ſuch as are at eaſe in Sion,<note place="margin">Amos 6.1, 6, 7.</note> and <hi>are not grieued for the affliction of Ioſeph:</hi> with the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:19558:8"/>iudgement following. <hi>Therefore now ſhall they goe captiue, with the first that goe captiue.</hi> We know the Angels bitter curſe againſt the inhabitants of Meroz.<note place="margin">Iudg. 5.23.</note> 
               <hi>Curſe ye Meroz (ſaid the Angell of the Lord) curſe ye bitterly the inhabitants thereof: becauſe they came not to helpe the Lord, to helpe the Lord against the mighty.</hi> Not as if the Lord did ſtand in need of our helpe, or were not able, without our aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, to maintaine his owne cauſe; but that hereby he would make triall of our readineſſe to doe him ſeruice, and proue the ſincerity of our loue. If wee hold our peace and ſit ſtill at this time,<note place="margin">Eſter 4 14.</note> deliuerance ſhall ariſe to Gods Church from another place: but let vs looke that the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction doe not light vpon vs and ours.</p>
            <p>I need not make any application of that which I haue ſpoken: the face of Chriſtendome, ſo miſerably rent and torne, as it is at this day, cannot but preſent it ſelfe as a rufull ſpectacle vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all our eyes, and (if there be any bowels in vs) ſtirre vp compaſſion in our hearts. Neither need I to be earneſt in exciting you to put your help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hands to the making vp of theſe breaches: your forwardneſſe herein hath preuented mee, and in ſtead of petitioning (for which I had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared my ſelfe) hath miniſtred vnto mee matter of thankeſgiuing. A good worke is at all times commendable: but the doing of it in fit time, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth much to the luſter thereof, and maketh it yet more goodly. The ſeaſon of the yeere is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proching, wherein <hi>Kings goe forth</hi> to battell:<note place="margin">2. Sam. 11.1.</note> the preſent ſupply and offer of your Subſidie was
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19558:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>done in a time moſt ſeaſonable: being ſo much al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the more acceptable, as it was granted <hi>not grudgingly, or of neceſsity,</hi> but freely, and with a willing minde. <hi>God loueth a cheerefull giuer:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 9.7, 8.</note> and he <hi>is able to make all grace abound towards you, that ye alwayes hauing all ſufficiency in all things, may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound to euery good worke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus being by your goodneſſe ſo happily abridged of that which I intended further to haue vrged from the coniunction which we haue with the <hi>Body:</hi> I paſſe now vnto the ſecond part of the Communion of Saints, which conſiſteth in the vnion which we all haue with one <hi>Head.</hi> For Chriſt our Head is the maine foundation of this heauenly vnion. Out of him there is nothing but confuſion; without him we are nothing but diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordered heapes of rubbiſh: but <hi>in him all the building fitly framed together, groweth vnto an holy Temple in the Lord;</hi> and <hi>in him are we builded toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for an habitation of God through the Spirit,</hi> Epheſ. 2.21, 22. Of our ſelues wee are but loſt ſheepe, ſcattered and wandring vpon euery Mountaine. From him it is, that there is <hi>one fold, and one ſhepheard,</hi> Ioh. 10.16. God hauing pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in himſelfe to <hi>gather together in one all things in Chriſt, both which are in heauen, and which are on earth, euen in him,</hi> Epheſ. 1.10. This is the effect of our Sauiours prayer, Ioh. 17.21. <hi>That they all may be one, as thou Father art in me, &amp; I in thee, that they alſo may be one in vs, &amp;c. I in them, and thou in me, that they may be made perfect in one.</hi> And this is it which we finde ſo oft repeated by Saint <hi>Paul: We
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19558:9"/>being many, are one body in Christ,</hi> Rom. 12.5. <hi>Ye are all one in Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> Gal. 3.28. And in the Text wee haue in hand: <hi>Wee being many, are one bread, and one body.</hi> Why? becauſe <hi>we are all partakers of that one bread:</hi> namely, of that bread, whereof he had ſaid in the words immediately going before: <hi>The bread which we breake,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cer. 10.16.</note> 
               <hi>is it not the communion of the body of Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Vnder the name of <hi>Bread</hi> therefore heere is comprehended both <hi>Panis Domini,</hi> and <hi>Panis Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus;</hi> not onely the bread of the Lord, but alſo the Lord himſelfe, who is that <hi>liuing Bread which came downe from heauen,</hi> Ioh. 6.51. For as Saint <hi>Peter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet 3.21.</note> ſaying that <hi>Baptiſme doth ſaue vs,</hi> vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth thereby both the outward part of that Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, (for he expreſſely calleth it a <hi>figure</hi>) and more then that too (as appeareth by the explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion preſently adioyned: <hi>not the putting away of the filth of the fleſh</hi>) euen the inward purging of our conſciences by vertue of the death and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of Ieſus Chriſt: ſo Saint <hi>Paul</hi> heere making the reaſon of our vnion to bee our <hi>parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king all of this one bread,</hi> hath not ſo much reſpect vnto the externall bread in the Sacrament (though he exclude not that neither) as vnto the true and heauenly Bread figured thereby; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Lord himſelfe pronounceth in the ſixth of <hi>Iohn:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 8.32, 51.</note> 
               <hi>The bread that I will giue, is my fleſh, which I will giue for the life of the world.</hi> And (to ſhew that by partaking of this bread, that wonderfull vnion we ſpeake of, is effected:) <hi>Hee that eateth my fleſh, and drinketh my blood,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 6.56.</note> 
               <hi>dwelleth in me, and I in him.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:19558:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> It is a lamentable thing to behold, how this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sacrament, which was ordained by Chriſt to be a bond whereby wee ſhould be knit together in vnity, is by Satans malice, and the corruption of mans diſpoſition, ſo ſtrangely peruerted the contrary way; that it is made the principall oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of that wofull diſtraction which wee ſee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Chriſtians at this day, and the very fuell of endleſſe ſtrifes, and implacable contentions. And for as much as theſe miſchiefes haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from the inconſiderate confounding of thoſe things which in their owne nature are as different as may be: for the cleerer diſtinguiſhing of matters, we are in the firſt place to conſider, that a Sacrament taken in his full extent, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendeth two things in it: that which is out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and viſible, which the Schooles call pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly <hi>Sacramentum,</hi> (in a more ſtrict acception of the word:) and that which is inward and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſible, which they tearme <hi>rem Sacramenti,</hi> the principall thing exhibited in the Sacrament. Thus in the Lords Supper, the outward thing which we ſee with our eyes, is <hi>bread and wine,</hi> the inward thing which wee apprehend by faith is, <hi>the body and blood of Chriſt:</hi> in the outward part of this myſticall action, which reacheth to that which is <hi>Sacramentum</hi> onely, we receiue this bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and blood but ſacramentally; in the inward, which containeth <hi>rem,</hi> the thing it ſelfe in it, wee receiue them really: and conſequently the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of theſe in the one is <hi>relatiue and ſymbolicall;</hi> in the other, <hi>reall and ſubſtantiall.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:19558:10"/>
            <p> To begin then with that which is ſymbolicall and relatiue: we may obſerue out of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which ſaith, that <hi>Abraham receiued the ſigne of Circumciſion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>a ſeale of the righteouſneſſe of the faith which hee had being vncircumciſed;</hi> that Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments haue a twofold relation to the things whereof they be Sacraments: the one of a <hi>ſigne,</hi> the other of a <hi>ſeale.</hi> Signes, wee knovv, are rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuely vnited vnto the things which they doe ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie; and in this reſpect are ſo neerly conioyned together, that the name of the one is vſually communicated vnto the other. <hi>This cup is the new Teſtament,</hi> or, the new Couenant, ſaith our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour in the inſtitution of the holy Supper, Luk. 22.20. <hi>This is my Couenant,</hi> ſaith God in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of Circumciſion in the old Teſtament, Gen. 17.10. but how it was his Couenant, hee explaneth in the verſe immediatly following: <hi>Ye ſhall circumciſe the fleſh of your foreskinne; and it ſhall be a</hi> SIGNE <hi>of the Couenant betwixt me and you.</hi> So words being the ſignes of things, no ſooner is the ſound of the word conueyed to our eares, but the notion of the thing ſignified there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by is preſented vnto our minde: and thereupon in the ſpeech of the Scripture nothing is more ordinary, then by the terme of<note n="*" place="margin">So the ten. Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Exod. 24.28. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, no thing. Luk. 1.37. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Word</hi> to note a <hi>thing.</hi> We reade in the fourth of the firſt of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel,</hi> that the Philiſtims were afraid and ſaid, <hi>God is come into the Campe,</hi> verſ. 7. when the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites brought thither <hi>the Arke of the Couenant of the Lord of hoſts, which dwelleth betweene the Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rubims,</hi> verſ. 4. and yet was that no other but this
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19558:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>relatiue kinde of preſence wherof now we ſpeake: in reſpect whereof alſo the <hi>ſhewbread</hi> is in the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew named <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>the bread of faces,</hi> or, <hi>the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence bread.</hi> Wee ſee with vs, the roome wherein the Kings chaire, and other enſignes of State are placed, is called <hi>the Chamber of preſence,</hi> although the King himſelfe bee not there perſonally preſent: and as the rude and vndutifull beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour of any in that place, or the offering of any diſ-reſpect to the Kings pourtraicture, or to the Armes Royall, or to any other thing that hath relation to his Maieſty, is taken as a diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour done vnto the King himſelfe: ſo heere, hee that eateth the bread, and drinketh the cup of the Lord vnworthily, is accounted guilty of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering indignity to the <hi>body and blood of the Lord.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.27.</note>
            </p>
            <p>In this ſort wee acknowledge Sacraments to be <hi>ſignes;</hi> but bare ſignes we denie them to bee: <hi>ſeales</hi> they are, as vvell as ſignes of the Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of grace. As it vvas therefore ſaid of <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptist,</hi> that he vvas <hi>a Prophet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 11.9.</note> 
               <hi>and more then a Prophet:</hi> ſo muſt vve ſay of Sacraments, that they be ſignes, and more then ſignes; euen pledges and aſſurances of the intereſt vvhich vvee haue in the heauenly things that are repreſented by them. He that hath in his chamber y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> picture of the French King, hath but a bare ſigne; vvhich poſſibly may make him thinke of that King vvhen hee looketh on it, but ſhevveth not that hee hath any manner of intereſt in him. It is othervviſe vvith him that hath the Kings great Seale for the confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the title that hee hath vnto all the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:19558:11"/>lands and liuelihood which he doth inioy. And as heere, the waxe that is affixed to thoſe letters Patents, howſoeuer for ſubſtance it bee the very ſame with that which is to be found euery where, yet being applyed to this vſe, is of more worth to the Patentee, then all the waxe in the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try beſide: ſo ſtandeth it with the outward ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the matter of the Sacrament. The bread and wine are not changed in ſubſtance from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame with that which is ſerued at ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry tables: but in reſpect of the ſacred vſe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto they are conſecrated, ſuch a change is made, that now they differ as much from common bread and wine, as heauen from earth. Neither are they to be accounted barely <hi>ſignificatiue,</hi> but truly <hi>exhibitiue</hi> alſo of thoſe heauenly things whereto they haue relation: as being appoynted by God to bee a meanes of conueying the ſame vnto vs, and putting vs in actuall poſſeſſion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. So that in the vſe of this holy ordinance, as verily as a man with his bodily hand and mouth receiueth the earthly creatures; ſo verily doth he with his ſpirituall hand and mouth (if any ſuch he haue) receiue the body and blood of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And this is that <hi>reall and ſubſtantiall</hi> preſence, which wee affirmed to be in the inward part of this ſacred action. For the better conceiuing of which myſtery, we are to inquire, firſt, what the thing is which wee doe heere receiue; ſecondly, how and in what manner we are made partakers of it. Touching the firſt, the truth which muſt be held, is this: that wee doe not here receiue onely
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:19558:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>the benefits that flow from Chriſt; but the very <hi>body and blood of Chriſt,</hi> that is, Chriſt himſelfe crucified. For as none can bee made partaker of the vertue of the bread and wine to his bodily ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtenance, vnleſſe he firſt doe receiue the ſubſtance of thoſe creatures: ſo neither can any participate in the benefits ariſing from Chriſt to his ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all reliefe, except he firſt haue communion with Chriſt himſelfe. We muſt<note n="a" place="margin">1. Ioh. 5.12.</note> 
               <hi>haue the Sonne,</hi> before wee <hi>haue life:</hi> and therefore<note n="b" place="margin">Ioh. 6.57.</note> 
               <hi>eate</hi> him we muſt, (as himſelfe ſpeaketh) that is, as truly bee made partakers of him, as we are of our ordinary food, if we will <hi>liue</hi> by him. As there is a giuing of him on Gods part (for<note n="c" place="margin">Eſa. 9.6.</note> 
               <hi>vnto vs a Sonne is giuen;</hi>) ſo there muſt bee a receiuing of him on our part: for<note n="d" place="margin">Ioh. 1.12.</note> 
               <hi>as many as receiued him, to them gaue hee power to become the ſonnes of God.</hi> And as wee are<note n="e" place="margin">1. Cor. 1.9.</note> 
               <hi>called by God vnto the communion of his Sonne Ieſus Christ our Lord:</hi> ſo if we doe heare his voyce, and not harden our hearts by vnbeliefe, wee are indeed made<note n="f" place="margin">Heb. 3.14.</note> 
               <hi>partakers of Christ.</hi> This is that <hi>great myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> (for ſo the Apoſtle termeth it) of our vnion with Chriſt,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.30, 32.</note> whereby we are made <hi>members of his body, of his fleſh, and of his bones:</hi> and this is that <hi>eating of the fleſh of the Sonne of man, and drinking of his blood,</hi> which our Sauiour inſiſteth ſo much vpon, in the ſixth of <hi>Iohn.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where if any man ſhall demand, (that I may now come vnto the ſecond poynt of our inquiry) <hi>How can this man giue vs his fleſh to eate?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 6.52.</note> he muſt beware that he come not pre-occupied with ſuch dull conceits as they were poſſeſſed withall, who
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:19558:12"/>moued that queſtion there; hee muſt not thinke that we cannot truly feed on Chriſt, vnleſſe we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue him within our iawes: (for that is as groſſe an imagination as that of <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> who could not conceiue how a man could bee <hi>borne againe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 2.4.</note> vnleſſe he ſhould <hi>enter the ſecond time into his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wombe:</hi>) but muſt conſider that the <hi>eating and drinking</hi> which our Sauiour ſpeaketh of, muſt be anſwerable to the <hi>hungring and thirsting,</hi> for the quenching whereof this heauenly Banquet is prouided. Marke well the words which he vſeth, toward the beginning of his diſcourſe concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this argument.<note place="margin">Ioh. 6.35, 36.</note> 
               <hi>I am the bread of life, hee that commeth to me, ſhall neuer hunger; and hee that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeueth on me, ſhall neuer thirſt. But I ſaid vnto you, that ye alſo haue ſeene me, and beleeue not.</hi> And com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare them with thoſe in the end:<note place="margin">Ioh. 6.63, 64.</note> 
               <hi>It is the Spirit that quickeneth, the fleſh profiteth nothing: the words that I ſpeake vnto you, they are ſpirit, and they are life. But there are ſome of you that beleeue not.</hi> Now obſerue, that ſuch as our hungring is, ſuch is our eating. But euery one will confeſſe, that the hunger heere ſpoken of, is not corporall, but ſpirituall: Why then ſhould any man dreame heere of a corporall eating? Againe, the corporall eating, if a man might haue it, would not auaile any thing to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſlaking of this hunger; nay, we are expreſſely told, that <hi>the fleſh</hi> thus taken (for ſo we muſt vnderſtand it) <hi>profiteth nothing,</hi> a man ſhould neuer be the better, nor one iot the holier, nor any whit further from the ſecond death, if he had filled his belly with it. But that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:19558:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>manner of feeding on this fleſh, which Chriſt himſelfe commendeth vnto vs, is of ſuch profit, that it preſerueth the eater from death,<note place="margin">Ioh. 6.50, 51, 54, 58.</note> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth him to liue for euer. It is not therefore ſuch an eating, that euery man who bringeth a bodily mouth with him may attaine vnto: but it is of a farre higher nature; namely, a ſpirituall vniting of vs vnto Chriſt, whereby he dwelleth in vs, and we liue by him.</p>
            <p>If any doe further inquire, how it is poſſible that any ſuch vnion ſhould be, ſeeing the body of Chriſt is in heauen, and wee are vpon earth? I anſwere, that if the manner of this coniunction were carnall and corporall, it would bee indeed neceſſary that the things conioyned ſhould bee admitted to bee in the ſame place: but it being altogether ſpirituall and ſupernaturall, no locall preſence, no phyſicall nor mathematicall conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity or contiguity is any way requiſite there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. It is ſufficient for the making of a reall vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in this kinde, that Chriſt and we (though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo farre diſtant in place each from other) bee knit together by thoſe ſpirituall ligatures, which are intimated vnto vs in the words alledged out of the ſixth of <hi>Iohn:</hi> to wit, the <hi>quickening Spirit</hi> deſcending downeward from the Head, to be in vs a fountaine of ſupernaturall life; and a <hi>liuely faith</hi> (wrought by the ſame Spirit) aſcending from vs vpward, to lay faſt hold vpon him, who <hi>hauing by himſelfe purged our ſinnes, ſitteth on the right hand of the Maiesty on high.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 1.3.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt therefore, for the communion of the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:19558:13"/>
               <hi>Spirit,</hi> which is the ground and foundation of this ſpirituall vnion; let vs call to minde what we haue read in Gods Booke: that Chriſt, the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> was made<note n="a" place="margin">1. Cor. 15.45.</note> 
               <hi>a quickening ſpirit:</hi> and that he<note n="b" place="margin">Ioh. 5.21.</note> 
               <hi>quickeneth whom he will:</hi> that vnto him<note n="c" place="margin">Ioh. 3.34.</note> 
               <hi>God hath giuen the Spirit without meaſure:</hi> and<note n="d" place="margin">Ioh. 1.16.</note> 
               <hi>of his fulneſſe haue all we receiued:</hi> that<note n="e" place="margin">1. Cor. 6.17.</note> 
               <hi>he that is ioyned vnto the Lord, is one Spirit:</hi> and that<note n="f" place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.24.4.13.</note> 
               <hi>heereby wee know that we dwell in him, and he in vs, becauſe hee hath giuen vs his Spirit.</hi> By all which it doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, that the myſtery of our vnion with Chriſt conſiſteth mainly in this: that the ſelfe-ſame Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit which is in him, as in the Head, is ſo deriued from him into euery one of his true members, that thereby they are animated and quickened to a ſpirituall life. We reade in the firſt of <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> of foure liuing creatures, and of foure wheeles ſtanding by them. <hi>When thoſe went,</hi> (ſaith the Text) <hi>theſe went; and when thoſe ſtood, theſe ſtood: and when thoſe were lifted vp from the earth, the wheeles were lifted vp ouer againſt them.</hi> Hee that ſhould behold ſuch a viſion as this, would eaſily conclude by y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which he ſaw, that ſome inuiſible bands there were by which theſe wheeles and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing creatures were ioyned together, howſoeuer none did outwardly appeare vnto the eye: and the holy Ghoſt, to giue vs ſatisfaction heerein, diſcouereth the ſecret, by yeelding this for the reaſon of this ſtrange connexion; that <hi>the ſpirit of the liuing creature was in the wheeles,</hi> Ezek. 1.21. From whence wee may inferre, that things may truly be conioyned together, though the manner
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:19558:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>of the coniunction bee not corporall: and that things diſtant in place may be vnited together, by hauing the ſpirit of the one communicated vnto the other.</p>
            <p>Nay, if we marke it well, we ſhall finde it to be thus in euery of our owne bodies: that the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall reaſon of the vnion of the members con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth not in the continuity of the parts (though that alſo be requiſite to the vnity of a naturall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy:) but in the animation thereof by one and the ſame ſpirit. If we ſhould ſuppoſe a body to be as high as the heauens, that the head thereof ſhould be where Chriſt our Head is, and the feet where we his members are: no ſooner could that head thinke of mouing one of the toes, but inſtantly the thing would be done, without any impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment giuen by that huge diſtance of the one from the other. And why? becauſe the ſame ſoule that is in the head, as in the fountaine of ſence and motion, is preſent likewiſe in the loweſt member of the body. But if it ſhould ſo fall out, that this, or any other member proued to be mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified, it preſently would ceaſe to bee a member of that body; the corporall coniunction and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuity with the other parts notwithſtanding. And euen thus is it in Chriſt; although in regard of his corporall preſence, <hi>the heauen muſt receiue him, vntill the times of the restitution of all things:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 3.21.</note> yet is he here <hi>with vs alway, euen vnto the end of the world,</hi> in reſpect of the preſence of his Spirit;<note place="margin">Math. 28.20.</note> by the vitall influence whereof from him, as from the Head, <hi>the whole body is fitly ioyned together,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.16.</note>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:19558:14"/>
               <hi>and compacted by that which euery ioynt ſupplieth, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the effectuall working in the meaſure of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery part.</hi> Which quickening Spirit if it be want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in any, no externall communion with Chriſt or his Church, can make him a true member of this myſticall body: this being a moſt ſure prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, that <hi>He which hath not the Spirit of Chriſt, is none of his,</hi> Rom. 8.9.</p>
            <p>Now among all the graces that are wrought in vs by the Spirit of Chriſt, the ſoule (as it were) of all the reſt, and that whereby<note n="a" place="margin">Habak. 2.4. Rom. 1.17. Gal. 3.11. Heb. 10.38.</note> 
               <hi>the iust doth liue,</hi> is Faith.<note n="b" place="margin">Gal. 5.5.</note> 
               <hi>For we through the Spirit waite for the hope of righteouſneſſe by faith,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Paul</hi> to the Galatians. And againe:<note n="c" place="margin">Gal. 2.20.</note> 
               <hi>I liue, yet not I, but Chriſt liueth in me; and the life which I now liue in the fleſh, I liue by the faith of the Sonne of God, who loued me, and gaue himſelfe for me.</hi> By faith it is, that wee doe<note n="d" place="margin">Ioh. 1.12.</note> 
               <hi>receiue</hi> Chriſt: and ſo likewiſe<note n="e" place="margin">Epheſ. 3.17.</note> Chriſt <hi>dwelleth in our hearts by faith.</hi> Faith there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is that ſpirituall mouth in vs, whereby wee <hi>eate the fleſh of the Sonne of man, and drinke his blood,</hi> that is, (as the Apoſtle expreſſeth it without the trope)<note n="f" place="margin">Heb. 3.14.</note> 
               <hi>are made partakers of Christ:</hi> he being by this meanes as truly, and euery wayes as effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally made ours, as the meate and drinke which we receiue into our naturall bodies.</p>
            <p>But you will ſay, If this be all the matter, what doe we get by comming to the Sacrament? ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we haue faith, and the quickening Spirit of Chriſt before wee come thither. To this I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere: that the Spirit is receiued in diuers mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and faith beſtowed vpon vs in different de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:19558:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>by reaſon whereof our coniunction with Chriſt may euery day bee made ſtraiter, and the hold which we take of him firmer. To receiue the Spirit<note n="g" place="margin">Ioh. 3.34.</note> 
               <hi>not by meaſure,</hi> is the priuiledge of our Head: we that<note n="h" place="margin">Ioh. 1.16.</note> 
               <hi>receiue out of his fulneſſe,</hi> haue not our portion of grace deliuered vnto vs all at once, but muſt daily looke for<note n="i" place="margin">Phil. 1.19.</note> 
               <hi>ſupply of the Spirit of Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> So alſo, while we are in this world,<note n="k" place="margin">Rom. 1.17.</note> 
               <hi>the righteouſneſſe of God is reuealed</hi> vnto vs <hi>from faith to faith,</hi> that is, from one degree and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of it to another: and conſequently, we muſt ſtill labour to<note n="l" place="margin">1. Theſ. 3.10.</note> 
               <hi>perfect that which is lacking in our faith,</hi> and euermore pray with the Apoſtles,<note n="m" place="margin">Luk. 17.5.</note> 
               <hi>Lord increaſe our faith.</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Coloſ. 2.6, 7.</note> As wee haue therefore <hi>receiued Chriſt Ieſus the Lord,</hi> ſo muſt wee <hi>walke in him; rooted and built vp in him, and ſtabliſhed in the faith:</hi> that wee<note n="o" place="margin">Epheſ. 4.15.</note> 
               <hi>may grow vp into him in all things, which is the Head.</hi> And to this end God hath ordained publike officers in his Church,<note n="p" place="margin">Eph. 4.12, 13.</note> 
               <hi>for the perfecting of the Saints for the worke of the miniſtery, for the edifying of the body of Christ, till we all come in the vnity of the faith, and of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Sonne of God, vnto a perfect man, vnto the meaſure of the ſtature of the fulneſſe of Christ:</hi> and hath accordingly<note n="q" place="margin">2. Cor. 3.6.</note> 
               <hi>made them able Miniſters of the Spirit that quickeneth,</hi> and<note n="r" place="margin">1. Cor. 3.5.</note> 
               <hi>Miniſters by whom we ſhould beleeue, euen as the Lord ſhall giue to euery man.</hi> When wee haue therefore receiued<note n="ſ" place="margin">Gal. 3.2.</note> the Spirit and<note n="t" place="margin">Ioh. 17.20.</note> Faith (and ſo ſpirituall life) by their miniſtery, we are not there to reſt; but<note n="u" place="margin">1. Pet. 2.2.</note> 
               <hi>as new borne babes we must deſire the ſincere milke of the Word, that we may grow thereby:</hi> and as growne
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:19558:15"/>men too, wee muſt deſire to be fed at the Lords Table, that by the ſtrength of that ſpirituall re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> we may be inabled to doe the Lords worke, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> may continually be nouriſhed vp thereby in the life of grace, vnto the life of glory.</p>
            <p>Neither muſt we heere with a fleſhly eye looke vpon the meaneneſſe of the outward elements, and haue this faithleſſe thought in our hearts, that there is no likelihood, a bit of bread, and a draught of wine ſhould be able to produce ſuch heauenly effects as theſe. For ſo we ſhould prooue our ſelues to be no wiſer than <hi>Naaman</hi> the Syri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an was,<note place="margin">2 King. 5.12, 13.</note> who hauing receiued direction from the man of God, that he ſhould waſh in Iordan ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen times, to be cleanſed of his Leproſie; replied with indignation, <hi>Are not Abana and Pharpar, riuers of Damaſcus, better then all the waters of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el? May I not waſh in them, and be cleane?</hi> But as his ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts did ſoberly aduiſe him then, <hi>If the Prophet had bid thee doe ſome great thing, wouldest thou not haue done it? How much rather then, when hee ſaith to thee, Waſh and be cleane?</hi> So giue mee leaue to ſay vnto you now: If the Lord had comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vs to doe ſome great thing, for the attaining of ſo high a good; ſhould not we willingly haue done it? How much rather then, when hee bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs to eate the bread, and drinke the wine that he hath prouided for vs at his owne Table, that by his bleſſing thereupon wee may grow in grace, and be preſerued both in body and ſoule vnto euerlaſting life?</p>
            <p>True it is indeed, theſe outward creatures haue
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:19558:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>no naturall power in them to effect ſo great a worke as this is, no more then the water of Ior<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan had to recouer the Leper: but the worke wrought by theſe meanes, is ſupernaturall; and God hath been pleaſed in the diſpenſation both of the Word and of the Sacraments ſo to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine it, that theſe heauenly treaſures ſhould bee preſented vnto vs <hi>in earthen veſſels,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.7.</note> 
               <hi>that the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of the power might be of God.</hi> As therefore in the preaching of the Goſpell, the Miniſter doth not <hi>dare verba,</hi> and beate the aire with a fruitleſſe ſound, but the words that hee ſpeaketh vnto vs are Spirit and life;<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.21.</note> 
               <hi>God being pleaſed by the fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of preaching, to ſaue them that beleeue:</hi> ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in the adminiſtration of the Lords Supper, he doth not feed vs with bare bread and wine, but if we haue the life of faith in vs, (for ſtill we muſt remember that this Table is prouided not for the dead, but for the liuing) and come worthily,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.16.</note> 
               <hi>the Cup of bleſsing which he bleſſeth,</hi> will be vnto vs <hi>the communion of the blood of Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>the bread which hee breaketh, the communion of the body of Chriſt:</hi> of which precious body and blood wee being really made partakers, (that is, in truth and indeed, and not in imagination onely) al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in a ſpirituall and not a corporall man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; the Lord doth <hi>grant vs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 3.16, 19.</note> 
               <hi>according to the riches of his glory, to bee ſtrengthened with might by his Spirit in the inner man,</hi> that we may <hi>bee filled with all the fulneſſe of God.</hi> For the Sacraments (as well as the Word) be a part of that <hi>ministration of the Spirit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 3.6, 8.</note> which is committed to the <hi>Miniſters of the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:19558:16"/>New Teſtament:</hi> for as much as <hi>by one Spirit,</hi> (as before we haue heard from the Apoſtle) <hi>wee haue been all baptized into one body,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 12.13.</note> 
               <hi>and haue been all made to drinke into one Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus haue I finiſhed the firſt part of my taske, my <hi>Congregatio homogeneorum,</hi> (as I call it) the knitting together of thoſe that appertaine to the ſame body, both with their fellovv-members, and vvith their Head: vvhich is the thing laid dovvne in the expreſſe vvords of my Text. It re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth novv that I proceed to the Apoſtles ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication hereof vnto the argument hee hath in hand, vvhich is <hi>Segregatio heterogeneorum,</hi> a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuering of thoſe that bee not of the ſame com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion; that the faithfull may not partake vvith Idolaters, by countenancing, or any vvay ioyning vvith them in their vngodly courſes. For that this is the maine ſcope at vvhich S. <hi>Paul</hi> aimeth in his treating here of the Sacrament, is euident both by that vvhich goeth before in the 19. verſ. <hi>Wherefore my dearely beloued, flee from Idolatry:</hi> and that vvhich follovveth in the 21. <hi>Yee cannot drinke the Cup of the Lord, and the cup of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels; ye cannot be partakers of the Lords Table, and of the table of diuels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereby vve may collect thus much, that as the Lords Supper is a ſeale of our coniunction one vvith another, and vvith Chriſt our Head; ſo is it an euidence of our diſ-iunction from Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters, binding vs to dis-auovv all communion vvith them in their falſe vvorſhip. And indeed, the one muſt neceſſarily follovv vpon the other:
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:19558:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>conſidering the nature of this hainous ſinne of Idolatry is ſuch, that it can no wayes ſtand with the fellowſhip which a Chriſtian man ought to haue, both with the Head, and with the body of the Church. To this purpoſe, in the ſixth of the ſecond to the Corinthians we reade thus: <hi>What agreement hath the Temple of God with Idols?</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 6.16, 17</note> 
               <hi>for ye are the Temple of the liuing God, as God hath ſaid, I will dwell in them, and walke in them, and I will bee their God, and they ſhall be my people. Wherefore come out from among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; be ye ſeparate, ſaith the Lord, and touch not the vncleane thing; and I will receiue you.</hi> And in the 2. Chap. of the Epiſtle to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſſians: <hi>Let no man beguile you of your reward,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 2.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 19.</note> 
               <hi>in a voluntary humility, and worſhipping of Angels, intru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding into thoſe things which he hath not ſeene, vainely puft vp by his fleſhly minde: and not holding the head, from which all the body by ioynts and bands hauing nouriſhment miniſtred, and knit together, increaſeth with the increaſe of God.</hi> In which words the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſheweth vnto vs, that ſuch as vnder pretence of humility were drawne to the worſhipping of Angels, did <hi>not hold the Head,</hi> and conſequently could not retaine communion with the <hi>body,</hi> which receiueth his whole growth from thence. Anſwerably whereunto the Fathers aſſembled out of diuers prouinces of Aſia in the Synode held at Laodicea, (not farre from the Coloſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans) did ſolemnely conclude, that<note n="a" place="margin">Concil. Laodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cen. Can. <hi>35.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: as Theodoret expoundeth theſe words of the Canon, in <hi>2.</hi> &amp; <hi>3.</hi> cap. epiſt. ad Coloſſ.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſtians ought not to forſake the Church of God, and goe and inuocate Angels,</hi> and pronounced an <hi>anathema</hi> againſt any that ſhould bee found to doe ſo,<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:19558:17"/>
               <hi>becauſe</hi> (ſay they) <hi>he hath forſaken our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, the Sonne of God, and giuen himſelfe to Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try:</hi> declaring plainly, that by this idolatrous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocation of Angels, a diſceſſion was made both from the <hi>Church</hi> of God, as they note in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, and from <hi>Chriſt</hi> the Head of the Church, as they obſerue in the end of their Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non.</p>
            <p>For the further vnderſtanding of this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, it will not be amiſſe to conſider what <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doret,</hi> a famous Biſhop of the ancient Church, hath written of this matter in his Commentary vpon the ſecond to the Coloſſians, <hi>They that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended the Law</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>induced the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo to worſhip the Angels, ſaying that the Law was giuen by them. And this vice continued in Phrygia, and Piſidia for a long time: for which cauſe alſo the Synod aſſembled in Laodicea the chiefe City of Phrygia, forbad them by a Law, to pray vnto Angels. And euen to this day among them and their borderers, there are Oratories of Saint</hi> Michael <hi>to be ſeene. This therefore did they counſell ſhould be done, vſing humility, and ſaying, that the God of all was inuiſible, and inacceſsible, and incomprehenſible; and that it was fit men ſhould get Gods fauour by the meanes of Angels.</hi> And this is it which the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>In humility, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping of Angels.</hi> Thus farre <hi>Theodoret,</hi> whom Cardinall <hi>Baronius</hi> diſcerning to come ſomwhat cloſe vnto him, and to touch the Idolatry of the Popiſh crue a little to the quicke, leaueth the poore ſhifts wherewith his companions labour to obſcure the light of this teſtimony, and telleth
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:19558:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>vs plainely, that<note n="c" place="margin">Ex his videas (quod neceſſariò dicendum est) Theodoretum haud ſatis ſeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citer (eius pace ſit dictum) aſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutum eſſe Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li verborum ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum. <hi>Baron. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. tom. 1. ann. 60. ſect. 20.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Theodoret, by his leaue, did not well vnderstand the meaning of Pauls words:</hi> and<note n="d" place="margin">Incautè nimis, quae à Catholicis eſſent antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tùs inſtituta, haereticis, quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum nulla eſſet memoria, tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buens. <hi>Id. ibid.</hi>
               </note> that thoſe Oratories of Saint <hi>Michael</hi> were erected <hi>anciently by Catholicks,</hi> and not by thoſe <hi>Hereticks</hi> which were condemned in the Councell of Lao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicea, as he miſtooke the matter. As if any wiſe man would bee perſwaded vpon his bare word, that the memory of things done in Aſia ſo long ſince, ſhould be more freſh in Rome at this day, then in the time of <hi>Theodoret,</hi> who liued twelue hundred yeeres agoe.</p>
            <p>Yet muſt I needs confeſſe, that hee ſheweth a little more modeſty heerein then <hi>Bellarmine</hi> his fellow-Cardinall doth; who would make vs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, that the place in the nineteenth of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelation, where the Angell ſaith to Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> that would haue worſhipped him, <hi>See thou doe it not, I am thy fellow-ſeruant, Worſhip God;</hi> maketh for them; and demandeth very ſoberly,<note n="e" place="margin">Cur nos repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendimur, qui facimus quod Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>annes fecit? num meliùs Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anne nôrunt Caluiníſtae, ſint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Angeli ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randi? <hi>Bellar. de Sanctor. Beatitud. lib. 1. cap. 14.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>why they ſhould be reprehended, who doe the ſame thing that Iohn did?</hi> and, <hi>whether the Caluinists knew better then Iohn, whether Angels were to bee adored or no?</hi> And as for inuocation of them, he telleth vs, that<note n="f" place="margin">Hîc apertè S. Iacob Angelum inuocauit. <hi>Id. ibid. cap. 19.</hi>
               </note> Saint <hi>Iacob</hi> plainly prayed vnto an Angell, in the 48. of Geneſis, when in bleſſing the ſonnes of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> hee ſaid, <hi>The Angell which deliuered me from all euill, bleſſe thoſe children.</hi> Whom for an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere we remit to Saint <hi>Cyril,</hi> (in the firſt Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the third booke of his <hi>Theſaurus</hi>) and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate him to tell vs, how neere of kinne hee is here to thoſe Hereticks of whom S. <hi>Cyril</hi> there ſpeaketh. His words bee theſe: <hi>That hee doth not
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:19558:18"/>meane</hi> (in that place, Geneſ. 48.16.) <hi>an Angell, as the</hi> HERETICKES <hi>vnderstand it, but the Sonne of God is manifest by this: that when hee had ſaid, [The Angel,] he preſently addeth, [who deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered mee from all euils.]</hi> Which Saint <hi>Cyril</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuppoſeth, no good Chriſtian will aſcribe to any but to God alone.</p>
            <p>But to come more neere yet vnto that which is Idolatry moſt properly: An <hi>Idoll</hi> (we muſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand) in the exact propriety of the terme, doth ſignifie any Image; but according to the Eccleſiaſticall vſe of the word, it noteth ſuch an Image as is ſet vp for religious adoration. And in this later ſence we charge the adherents of the Church of Rome with groſſe Idolatry:<note place="margin">See for this, the excellent Homily of the Perill of Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry.</note> becauſe that contrary to Gods expreſſe Commandement they are found to bee worſhippers of Images. Neither will it auaile them heere to ſay, that the Idolatry forbidden in the Scripture, is that onely which was vſed by Iewes and Pagans. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle indeed in this place dehorting Chriſtians from Idolatry, propoundeth the fall of the Iewes in this kinde before their eyes:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.7, 8.</note> 
               <hi>Neither be yee Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>as ſome of them</hi> were. And ſo doth hee alſo adde concerning another ſinne, in the verſe following: <hi>Neither let vs commit fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as ſome of them committed.</hi> As well then might one pleade, that Iewiſh or Heatheniſh fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion were here onely reprehended, as Iewiſh or Heatheniſh Idolatry. But as the one is a foule ſinne, whether it bee committed by Iew, Pagan, or Chriſtian: ſo if ſuch as profeſſe the Name of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:19558:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>Chriſt, ſhall practiſe that which the Word of God condemneth in Iewes and Pagans, for Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, their profeſſion is ſo farre from diminiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that it augmenteth rather the hainouſneſſe of the crime.<note place="margin">Pſal. 135.15.</note> 
               <hi>The Idols of the Heathen are ſiluer and gold, the worke of mens hands,</hi> ſaith the Pſalmiſt: and ſo the <hi>Idols</hi> (of Chriſtians, in all likelihood) mentioned in the Reuelation,<note place="margin">Reuel. 9.20.</note> are ſaid to bee <hi>of gold, and ſiluer, and braſſe, and ſtone, and of wood; which neither can ſee, nor heare, nor walke.</hi> The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of theſe Idols (wee ſee) agreeth in all poynts with Popiſh Images: where is any diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence?</p>
            <p>The Heathen, ſay they, held the Images them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to be gods, which is far from our thought. Admit, ſome of the ſimpler ſort of the Heathen did ſo: what ſhall we ſay of the Iewiſh Idolaters, (of whom the Apoſtle here ſpeaketh) who erected the golden Calfe in the Wilderneſſe? Can wee thinke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they were all ſo ſenſeleſſe, as to imagine that the Calfe, which they knew was not at all <hi>in rerum naturâ,</hi> and had no being at that time when they came out of Egypt, ſhould yet be that <hi>God which brought them vp out of the land of Egypt?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 32.4.</note> And for the Heathen: did the Romans and Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians, when they dedicated in ſeuerall places an hundred Images (for example) to the honour of <hi>Iupiter,</hi> the king of all their gods, think that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they had made an hundred <hi>Iupiters?</hi> or when their blocks were ſo old, that they had need to haue new placed in their ſtead; did they think by this change of their Images, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they made change
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:19558:19"/>alſo of their gods? without queſtion they muſt ſo haue thought, if they did take the very Images themſelues to be their gods: and yet the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet bids vs conſider diligently; and wee ſhall finde that the Heathen nations <hi>did not change their gods,</hi> (Ierem. 2.10, 11.) Nay, what doe we meet with, more vſually in the writings of the Fathers, then theſe anſwers of the Heathens for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues?<note n="a" place="margin">Deos per ſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacra venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur. Arnob. lib. <hi>6.</hi> aduerſ. Getes.</note> 
               <hi>Wee worſhip the gods by the Images.</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Non ipſa, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, timemus; ſed eos, ad quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum imaginem ficta, et quorum nominibus co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crata ſunt. Lact. lib. <hi>2.</hi> diuin. inſtitut. ca. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Wee feare not them, but thoſe to whoſe image they are made, and to whoſe names they are conſecrated.</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Non ego illum lapidem colo. nec illud ſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crum quod eſt ſine ſenſu. Aug. in Pſal. <hi>96.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>I doe not worſhip that ſtone, nor that Image which is without ſenſe.</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Nec ſimulacru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nec daemonium colo; ſed per eſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giem corporalem eius rei ſignum intueor, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lere debeo. Aug. in Pſa. <hi>113.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>I neither worſhip the Image nor a ſpirit in it: but by the bodily pourtrature I doe behold the ſigne of that thing which I ought to worſhip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But admit they did not account the Image it ſelfe to be God, (will the Papiſt further ſay;) yet were thoſe images ſet vp to repreſent either things that had no being, or diuels, or falſe gods; and in that reſpect were Idols: wheras we erect Images onely to the honour of the true God, and of his ſeruants the Saints and Angels. To this I might oppoſe that anſwere of the Heathen to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians:<note n="e" place="margin">Non colimus niala daemonia: Angelos quos di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citis, ipſos et nos colimus, virtutes Dei magni, et mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſteria Dei magni. Aug. in Pſa. <hi>96.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>We doe not worſhip euill ſpirits: ſuch as you call Angels, thoſe doe we alſo worſhip, the powers of the great God, and the Miniſters of the great God.</hi> and put them in minde of S. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> reply:<note n="f" place="margin">Vtinam ipſos colere velletis; facilè ab ipſis diſceretis non illos colere. Aug. in Pſal. <hi>96.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>I would you did worſhip them; you ſhould eaſily learne of them not to worſhip them.</hi> But I will grant vnto them, that many of the Idolatrous Iewes &amp; Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens Images were ſuch as they ſay they were: yet I deny that all of them were ſuch, and confidently
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:19558:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>doe auouch, that Idolatry is commited by yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding adoration to an Image of the true God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. For proofe whereof (omitting the Idoles of<note n="g" place="margin">Iudg. 17.3, 13</note> 
               <hi>Micah,</hi> and<note n="h" place="margin">2. Kin. 10.16, 29, 31.</note> 
               <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> which were erected to the memory of <hi>Iehouah</hi> the God of Iſrael; as alſo the Athenians ſuperſtitious worſhip of the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Trehellius Pollio,</hi> in the life of Claudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, calleth the God of Moſes, <hi>incertum nume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> ſo doth Lucan the god of the Iewes, <hi>Incerti Iudaea Dei.</hi> As therefore the Iewes (by the relation of Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citus, li. 2. Hi.) worſhipped their God in mount Carmel, <hi>non ſimulacro aut templo, ſed ará tantùm:</hi> ſo it might bee that the Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians alſo did the like, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that their <hi>Ara miſericor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia</hi> (which poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly might be the ſame with this) is thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius. lib. 12. Thebaidos: <hi>Nulla aute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies, nulli co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa metallo Forma Dei; me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare et pectora gaudet.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne God,</hi> Act. 17.23. if, as the common vſe of Idolaters was, they added an Image to their Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar:) I will content my ſelfe with theſe two places of Scripture; the one whereof concerneth the Iewes, the other the Heathen. That which toucheth the Heathen, is in the firſt Chapter of the Epiſtle to the Romans: where the Apoſtle hauing ſaid, that God had ſhewed vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that which might be knowne of him; and that <hi>the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſible things of him,</hi> that is, <hi>his eternall power and God-head,</hi> was manifeſted vnto them by the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the world, and the contemplation of the creatures: hee addeth preſently, that God was ſorely diſpleaſed with them, and therefore gaue them vp vnto vile affections, becauſe <hi>they changed the glory of that vncorruptible God, into an Image made like to corruptible men, and to birds, and foure-footed beasts, and creeping things.</hi> Whereby it is euident, that the Idolatry condemned in the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt of the Heathen, was the adoring of the inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible God, whom they acknowledged to be the Creator of all things, in viſible Images faſhioned to the ſimilitude of men and beaſts.</p>
            <p>The other place of Scripture, is the 4. of Deuteronomy: where <hi>Moſes</hi> vſeth this ſpeech vnto the children of Iſrael.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:19558:20"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>The Lord ſpake vnto you out of the midſt of the firſt: yee heard the voyce of the Words, but ſaw no ſimilitude, onely yee heard a voyce,</hi> verſe 12. And what doth he inferre vpon this? <hi>Take yee therefore good heed vnto your ſelues,</hi> (ſaith he in the 5. verſe,) <hi>for he ſaw no manner of ſimilitude on the day that the Lord ſpake vnto you in Horeb, out of the midſt of the fire: Leſt yee corrupt your ſelues, and make you a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen image, the ſimilitude of any figure, the likeneſſe of male or female, the likenes of any beaſt that is on the earth, the likenes of any winged fowle that flieth in the aire, the likeneſſe of any thing that creepeth on the ground, the likenes of any fiſh that is in the waters be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath the earth.</hi> Where we may obſerue: firſt, that God in the deliuery of the Law did purpoſely vſe a <hi>voyce</hi> onely; becauſe that ſuch a creature as that, was not to be expreſſed by viſible lineaments: as if that voyce ſhould haue ſaid vnto the Painter, as Echo is fayned to doe in the<note n="i" place="margin">Auſonius, Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gram. xi.</note> Poet.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Vane, quid affectas faciem mihi ponere, pictor?</l>
               <l>Si mihi vis ſimilem pingere, pinge ſonum.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Secondly, that when he vttered the word of the ſecond Commandement in mount Sinai, and forbad the making of the likenes of any thing <hi>that is in Heauen aboue, or in the Earth beneath, or in the Waters vnder the Earth;</hi> hee did at that time for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare to ſhew himſelfe in any viſible ſhape, either of man or woman, either of beaſt in the earth, foule in the aire, or fiſh in the waters beneath the earth: to the end it might be the better made knowne, that it was his pleaſure not to be adored at all in any ſuch formes; &amp; that the worſhipping
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:19558:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>of Images, not onely as they haue reference to the creatures whom they doe immediately repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, or to falſe gods, but alſo as they haue relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to himſelfe (the true God, who was then ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vnto them in the Mount) did come within the compaſſe of the Idolatry which was condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in that Commandement.</p>
            <p>In vaine therefore doe the Romaniſts goe a bout to perſwade vs, that their Images be no I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doles: and as vainely alſo doe they ſpend time in curiouſly diſtinguiſhing the ſeuerall degrees of worſhip; the higheſt point whereof, which they call <hi>Latreia,</hi> and acknowledge to be due onely vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, they would be loth wee ſhould thinke that they did communicate to any of their Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. But here wee are to vnderſtand, firſt of all, that Idolatry may be committed by giuing not the higheſt onely, but alſo the loweſt degree of religious adoration vnto Images: and therefore in the words of the Commandement, the very <hi>bowing downe vnto them,</hi> which is one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meaneſt degrees of worſhip, is expreſly forbidden. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, that it is<note n="*" place="margin">Conſtans eſt Theologoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia, Imagine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eodem honore et cultu honorari et coli, quo coli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur id cuius eſt Imago. Azor. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitut. moral. part. <hi>1.</hi> lib. <hi>9.</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> the receiued doctrine of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh diuines, that the Image ſhould be honored with the ſame worſhip, wherewith that thing is worſhipped whoſe Image it is: and therfore what adoration is due to Chriſt and the Trinity, the ſame by this ground they are to giue vnto their Images. Thirdly, that in the Roman Pontificall publiſhed by the authority of <hi>Clement</hi> the VIII. (to omit other teſtimonies in this kinde) it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded,<note n="*" place="margin">Crux legati, quia debetur ei latria, erit à dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tris. Pontifical. edit. Rom. pag. <hi>672.</hi>
               </note> that the Croſſe of the Popes Legate ſhal
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:19558:21"/>haue the right hand, vpon this very reaſon, <hi>quia de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betur ei latria,</hi> becauſe the worſhip proper to God is due to it. Now whether they commit Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, who communicate vnto a ſenſeleſſe thing, that worſhip which they themſelues confeſſe to be due vnto God alone: let all the world iudge.</p>
            <p>They were beſt therefore from henceforth confeſſe themſelues to be Idolaters: and ſtand to it, that euery kinde of Idolatry is not vnlawfull. Their Ieſuite <hi>Gregorius de Valentia</hi> will tell them for their comfort,<note place="margin">Grego. Valent. li. 2. Apol. de Idololatr. ca. 7.1. Pe. 4.3.</note> that it is no abſurdity to thinke that Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> when he deterreth the faithfull by name <hi>ab illicitis Idolorum cultibus</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Saint <hi>Peter</hi> calleth them, that is, <hi>abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Idolatries</hi>) doth inſinuate therby, that<note n="*" place="margin">Some <hi>Jdola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try</hi> he ſhould ſay: for that is S. Peters word.</note> ſome worſhip of Images is lawfull. <hi>Iohn Monceye</hi> the Frenchman in his <hi>Aaron Purgatus</hi> (dedicated to the late Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the fifth) and in his twenty queſtions propounded to <hi>Viſorius,</hi> ſtretcheth yet a ſtraine higher. For howſoeuer hee cannot away with the name of Idols and Idolatry; yet he li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the thing it ſelfe ſo well, that he vndertaketh to cleare <hi>Aaron</hi> from committing any error in ſetting vp the golden Calfe, and laboureth to purge <hi>Laban,</hi> and <hi>Micha,</hi> and <hi>Ieroboam</hi> too from the imputation of Idolatry: hauing found in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, that nothing had beene done by them in this kinde, which is not agreeable to the practice of the Romane Church at this day.</p>
            <p>And leſt the poore people, whom they haue ſo miſerably abuſed, ſhould finde how farre they haue beene miſled; wee ſee that the maſters of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:19558:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>that Church doe in the Seruice books and Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſmes, which come vnto the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of the vulgar, generally leaue out the words of the ſecond Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement that make againſt the adoration of Images: fearing leſt by the light thereof, the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of their iniquity ſhould be diſcouered. They pretend indeed that this Commandement is not excluded by them, but included onely in the firſt: whereas in truth they doe but craftily conceale it from the peoples eyes, becauſe they would not haue them to be ruled by it. Nay,<note place="margin">Gab. Vaſquez. lib. 2. do Ador. diſput. 4. c. 3. §. 74.75.</note> 
               <hi>Vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quez</hi> the Ieſuite doth boldly acknowledge, that it plainely appeareth by comparing the words of this Commandement, with the place which hath beene alledged out of the 4. of Deuteronomy; that the Scripture did not onely forbid the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping of an Image for God, but alſo the ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the true God himſelfe in an Image. He confeſſeth further, that he and his fellow Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes doe otherwiſe. What ſaith hee then to the Commandement, thinke you? Becauſe it will not be obeyed, it muſt be repealed, and not admitted to haue any place among the morall precepts of God.<note n="*" place="margin">Cùm ſuerit iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris poſitiui et Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonialis illa leges Moſaicae prohibitio, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore legis Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicae debuit ceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſare; at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> id, quod aliâs iure natu rali licitum, et honeſtum eſt, vt imagines depin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere, et illis etia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vti ad adoratio nem, in lege E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangelie â locum habere debet. Vaſques ibid. c. <hi>4 §. 84.</hi>
               </note> It was (ſaith he) a poſitiue and ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall Law: and therefore ought to ceaſe in the time of the Goſpell. And as if it had not beene enough for him to match the Scribes and Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in impiety, who <hi>made the Commandement of God of none effect, that they might keepe their owne tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> that he might fulfill the meaſure of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and ſhew himſelfe to be a true childe of her who beareth the name of being <hi>the mother of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:19558:22"/>harlots and abominations of the earth;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reu. 17.5.</note> he is yet more mad,<note place="margin">Vaſquez de A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorat. lib. <hi>3.</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>put. <hi>1.</hi> Cap. <hi>2 § 5.8.10.</hi>
               </note> and ſticketh not to maintaine, that not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a paynted Image, but any other thing of the world, whether it be without life and reaſon, or whether it be a reaſonable creature, may (in the nature of the thing, and if the matter bee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creetly handled) be adored vvith God, as his Image; yea and counteth it no abſurdity at all, that a very vviſpe of ſtravv ſhould be thus vvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped.</p>
            <p>But let vs turne yet againe,<note place="margin">E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 8.15.</note> and vve ſhall ſee greater abominations then theſe. We heard hovv this bleſſed Sacrament, vvhich is here propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Apoſtle, as a bond to vnite Chriſtians together in one body, hath beene made the apple of ſtrife, and the occaſion of moſt bitter breaches in the Church: we may now obſerue againe, that the ſame holy Sacrament, which by the ſame A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle is here brought in as a principall induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to make men <hi>ſtee from Idolatry,</hi> is by our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries made the obiect of the groſſeſt Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try that euer hath been practiſed by any. For their conſtant doctrine is, that in worſhipping the Sacrament they ſhould giue vnto it, <hi>latriae cultum qui vero Deo debetur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>il. Trident. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſſ. <hi>13.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>1.5.</hi>
               </note> (as the Councell of Trent hath determined,) <hi>that kinde of ſeruice which is due to the true God;</hi> determining their worſhip in that very thing which the Prieſt doth hold betwixt his hands. Their practice alſo runs accordingly: for an inſtance whereof we neede goe no further then to <hi>Sanders</hi> booke of the Lords Supper; before which he hath perfixed
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:19558:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>an Epiſtle Dedicatory, ſuperſcribed in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: <hi>To the Body and Blood of our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, vnder the formes of Bread and Wine, all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, praiſe, and thankes, be giuen for euer.</hi> Adding further in the proceſſe of that blockiſh Epiſtle. <hi>Howſoeuer it be with other men, I adore thee my God and Lord really preſent vnder the formes of Bread and Wine, after conſecration denly made: Beſeeching thee of pardon for my ſinnes, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if the conceite which theſe men haue concerning the Sacrament ſhould proue to bee falſe (as indeed we know it to be moſt abſurd and monſtrous) their owne Ieſuite <hi>Coſter</hi> doth freely confeſſe, that they ſhould be in ſuch an <hi>error and Idolatry, qualis in orbe terrarum nunquam vel viſus vel auditus fuit, as neuer was ſeene or heard of in this world.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Tolerabilior eſt enim error e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum, qui pro Deo colunt Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> auream aut argenteam, aut alterius materiae imaginem, quo modo Gentiles deos ſuos vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabantur; vel pannum rubrum in haſtam eleua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, quod narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur de Lappis; vel viua anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia, vt quondam Egyptij: quàm eoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, qui fruſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> panis. Coſter. En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chirid. ca. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>For the error of them is more tolerable,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>who worſhip for God a Statue of gold or ſiluer, or an Image of any other matter, as the Gentiles adored their gods; or a red cloth lifted vp vpon a ſpeare, as it is reported of the Lappians; or liuing creatures, as did ſometime the Egyptians; then of thoſe that worſhip a piece of bread.</hi> We therefore who are verily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that the Papiſts doe thus, muſt of force (if we follow their Ieſuites direction) iudge them to be the moſt intolerable Idolaters that euer were.</p>
            <p>Nay, according to their owne principles, how is it poſſible that any of themſelues ſhould cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly know, that the hoſt which they worſhip ſhould be any other thing but bread? ſeeing the change doth wholy depend vpon <hi>conſecration
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:19558:23"/>duly made,</hi> (as <hi>Sanders</hi> ſpeaketh) and that depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vpon the intention of the Prieſt, which no man but himſelfe can haue notice of. <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> diſputing againſt <hi>Ambroſius Catharinus,</hi> one of his owne brethren, that a man hath no certaine knowledge of his owne iuſtification, can take ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage of this, and alledge for himſelfe, that one<note n="*" place="margin">Neque poteſt certus eſſe certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudine ſidei, ſe percipere verum Sacramentum; cum Sacramen tum ſine inten tione miniſtri non conficiatur, &amp; intentionem alterius nemo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>idere poſſit. <hi>Bellarmin de Iuſtificat. lib. 3. cap. 8.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>cannot be certaine by the certainty of faith, that hee doth receiue a true Sacrament; foraſmuch as the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament cannot be made without the intention of the Miniſter, and none can ſee another mans intention.</hi> Apply this now to the matter we haue in hand; and ſee into what intricate Labyrinths theſe men haue brought themſelues. Admit the Prieſts in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention ſtood right at the time of conſecration, yet if he that baptized him failed in his intention when he adminiſtred that Sacrament, he remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſtill vnbaptized, and ſo becommeth vncapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of Prieſthood; and conſequently, whatſoeuer he conſecrateth is but bread ſtill. Yea, admit hee were rightly baptized too: if either the Biſhop that conferred vpon him the Sacrament of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, (for ſo they hold it to be) or thoſe that bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized or ordained that Biſhop, miſſed their right intention; neither will the one proue Biſhop, nor the other Prieſt; and ſo with what intention ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer either the one or the other doth conſecrate, there remaineth but bread ſtill. Neither doth the inconuenience ſtay heere, but aſcendeth vpward to all their predeceſſors: in any one of whom if there fall out to bee a nullity of Prieſthood (for want of intention, either in the baptizer, or in the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:19558:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>ordainer) all the generation following, according to their principles, goe without their Prieſthood too; and ſo deliuer but bread to the people, in ſtead of the body of Chriſt. The Papiſts them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues therefore, if they ſtand vnto their owne grounds, muſt needs confeſſe, that they are in no better caſe heere, then the Samaritans were in, of whom our Sauiour ſaith,<note place="margin">Ioh. 4.22.</note> 
               <hi>Yee worſhip yee know not what:</hi> but we know, that what they worſhip (bee the condition or intention of their Prieſt what it will be) is bread indeed; which while they take to be their God, we muſt ſtill account them guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ſpirituall fornication, <hi>and ſuch fornication, as is not ſo much as named amongst the Gentiles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe then being the <hi>Idolaters</hi> with whom we haue to deale, let vs learne firſt how dangerous a thing it is to communicate with them in their falſe worſhip. For if we will be partakers of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylons ſinnes,<note place="margin">Reuel. 18.4.</note> wee muſt looke to receiue of her plagues. Secondly, wee are to be admoniſhed, that it is not ſufficient that in our owne perſons we refraine worſhipping of Idols, but it is fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther required, that we reſtraine (as much as in vs lyeth) the practice thereof in others; leſt by ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering God to be diſhonoured in ſo high a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, when wee may by our calling hinder it, wee make our ſelues partakers of other mens ſinnes. <hi>Eli</hi> the high Prieſt was a good man, and gaue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent counſell vnto his lewd ſonnes: yet wee know what iudgement fell vpon him,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 3.13.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe his ſonnes made themſelues vile, and he frowned not vpon them,</hi> (that is, reſtrained them not;) which God
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:19558:24"/>doth interpret to be a kinde of Idolatry,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 2.29.</note> in <hi>honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of his ſonnes aboue him.</hi> The Church of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gamus did for her owne part hold faſt Chriſts name, and denyed not his faith: yet had the Lord ſomething againſt her;<note place="margin">Reuel. 2.14.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe ſhe had there, them that held the doctrine of Balaam, who taught Balac to cast a ſtumbling blocke before the children of Iſrael, to eate things ſacrificed vnto Idols, and to commit fornication.</hi> So we ſee what ſpeciall notice our Sauiour taketh of the workes, and charity, and ſeruice, and faith, &amp; patience of the Church of Thyatira:<note place="margin">Reuel. 2.20.</note> and yet for all this he addeth, <hi>Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, I haue a few things againſt thee, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou ſufferest that woman Iezebel, which calleth herſelfe a Propheteſſe, to teach and to ſeduce my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants to commit fornication, and to eate things ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiced vnto Idols.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the ſecond of Iudges God telleth the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Iſrael, what miſchiefe ſhould come vnto them by tolerating the Canaanitiſh Idolaters in their Land.<note place="margin">Iudg. 2.3.</note> 
               <hi>They ſhall be</hi> thornes <hi>in your ſides,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and their gods ſhall be a ſnare vnto you.</hi> Which words containe in them the intimation of a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble danger: the one reſpecting the <hi>ſoule,</hi> the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>body.</hi> That which concerneth the ſoule, is: that their Idols ſhould be <hi>a ſnare vnto them.</hi> For God well knew that mans nature is as prone to ſpirituall fornication, as it is to corporall. As therefore for the preuenting of the one, he would not haue a common harlot tolerated in Iſrael, <hi>Lest the Land ſhould fall to whoredome and become full of wickedneſſe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Leuit. 19.29.</note> ſo for the keeping out of the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:19558:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>other, he would haue prouocations taken away, and all occaſions whereby a man might be temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to commit ſo vile a ſinne. The bodily danger that followeth vpon the toleration of Idolaters, is: that <hi>they ſhould be in their ſides,</hi> that is, (as in another place it is more fully expreſſed) <hi>they ſhould be prickes in their eyes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Numb. 33.55.</note> 
               <hi>and thornes in their ſides, and ſhould vexe them in the Land wherein they dwelled.</hi> Now in both theſe reſpects it is certaine, that the toleration of the Idolaters with whom we haue to doe, is farre more perillous than of any other. In regard of the ſpirituall danger, wherewith ſimple ſoules are more like to bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnared: becauſe this kinde of Idolatry is not brought in with an open ſhew of impiety, (as that of the Pagans) but is <hi>a myſtery of iniquity,</hi> a wickedneſſe couered with the vaile of piety; and the harlot, which maketh the inhabitants of the earth drunke with the wine of this fornication, is both gilded her ſelfe, and preſenteth alſo her abominations vnto her followers in <hi>a cup of gold.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reuel. 17.2.4.</note> If we looke to outward perill, we are like to find theſe men, not thornes in our ſides to vexe vs, but daggers in our hearts to deſtroy vs. Not that I take all of them to be of this furious diſpoſition, (miſtake me not: I know a number my ſelfe of a farre different temper:) but becauſe there are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer wanting among them ſome turbulent hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, ſo inflamed with the ſpirit of fornication, that they runne mad with it; and are tranſported ſo farre, that no tolerable termes can content them, vntill they haue attained to the vtmoſt
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:19558:25"/>pitch of their vnbridled deſires. For compaſſing whereof, there is no trechery, nor rebellion, nor murther, nor deſperate courſe whatſoeuer, that (without all remorſe of conſcience) they dare not aduenture vpon.</p>
            <p>Neither <hi>doe</hi> they thus only, but they <hi>teach</hi> men alſo ſo to doe: arming both Pope, and Biſhops, and People, and priuate perſons, with power to caſt downe euen Kings themſelues from their Thrones, if they ſtand in their way, and giue any impediment to their deſignes. Touching the Popes power herein, there is no diſputing: one of them telleth vs, that<note n="a" place="margin">Dubium non eſt, quin Papa poſſit omnes Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, cùm ſubeſt cauſa rationabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis, deponere. <hi>Auguſtin. Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphus, de Poteſt. Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſt. quaeſt. 46. artic. 2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>there is no doubt, but the Pope may depoſe all Kings, when there is a reaſonable cauſe ſo to doe.</hi> For Biſhops, Cardinall <hi>Baronius</hi> informeth vs by the example of <hi>Dacius</hi> the Biſhop of Millayne, his dealing againſt the Arrians;<note n="b" place="margin">Quo exemplo ſatis intelligas, non moereri ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumaiam, neque inuidiam Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copos illos pati debere, qui ne ſub haeretico principe degant, omnem lapidem voluunt. <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron. an. 538. §. 89.</hi>
               </note> that <hi>thoſe Biſhops deſerue no blame, and ought to ſuffer no enuie, who roll euery ſione,</hi> (yea and rather then faile, would blow vp ſtones too) <hi>that they may not liue vnder an hereticall Prince.</hi> For the People, <hi>Dominieus Bannes,</hi> a Dominican Friar, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolues, that they need not, in this caſe, expect any ſentencing of the matter by Pope, or other; but<note n="c" place="margin">Quando adeſt euidens notitia criminis, licitè poſſunt ſubditi (ſi modò eis vires ſuppetant) eximere ſe à poteſtate ſuorum Principum ante Judicis ſententiam deciaratoriam. <hi>Bannes in Thom. 2.2. quaeſt. 12. artic. 2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>when the knowledge of the fault is euident, ſubiects may lawfully (if ſo be they haue ſufficient ſtrength) exempt themſelues from ſubiection to their Princes, before any declaratory ſentence of a Iudge.</hi> And that we may vnderſtand that the <hi>Prouiſo</hi> which hee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerteth
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:19558:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>of hauing ſtrength ſufficient,</hi> is very mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall; he putteth vs in minde, that<note n="d" place="margin">Ex hâc con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſione ſequitur eſſe excuſandos Anglicanos &amp; Saxonios fideles, qui non ſe exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munt à poteſtate ſuperiorum, nec bellum contra illos gerunt. Quoniam com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muniter non ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent facultatem ad haec bella ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renda contra Principes, &amp; imminent illis grauia pericula. <hi>Id. Ibid.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>the faithfull</hi> (the Papiſts he meaneth) <hi>of England are to bee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed hereby, who doe not exempt themſelues from the power of their ſuperiours, nor make warre againſt them. Becauſe that generally they haue not power ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to make ſuch warres againſt Princes, and great dangers are imminent ouer them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, for priuate perſons, wee may reade in <hi>Suarez,</hi> that an hereticall King,<note n="e" place="margin">Poſt ſententi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am latam omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nò priuatur reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no, ita vt non poſſit iuſto titulo illud poſſidere: ergo extunc po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terit tanquam omninò tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus tractari; &amp; conſequenter à quocunque pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uato poterit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter fici. <hi>Fr. Sua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rez Defenſ. fid. Cathol. lib. 6. cap. 4. §. 14.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>after ſentence gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen againſt him, is abſolutely depriued of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, ſo that he cannot poſſeſſe it by any iuſt title: and therfore from thenceforth may be handled altogether as a Tyrant; and conſequently, hee may bee killed by any priuate perſon.</hi> Onely the Ieſuite addeth this limitation: that<note n="f" place="bottom">Si Papa Regem deponat, ab illis tantùm poterit expelli, vel interfi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i, qui bus ipſe id commiſerit. Quod ſinulli executionem imperet, pertinebit ad legitimum in regno ſucceſſorem; vel ſi nullus inuentus fuerit, ad regnum ipſum ſpectabit. <hi>Id. ibid. §. 18.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>If the Pope doe depoſe the King, he may be expelled or killed by them onely to whom hee ſhall commit that buſineſſe. But if he inioyne the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution thereof to no body; then it ſhall appertaine to the lawfull ſucceſſor in the Kingdome: or if none ſuch be to be found, it ſhall belong to the Kingdome it ſelfe.</hi> But let him once be declared to be a Tyrant; <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riana</hi> (<hi>Suarez</hi> his Country-man and fellow Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuite) will tell you better how hee ſhould bee handled.<note n="g" place="bottom">Jtaque apertâ vi &amp; armis poſſe occidi tyrannum, ſiue impetu in regiam facto, ſiue commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sâ pugnâ, in confeſſo eſt Sed &amp; dolo atque inſidijs exceptum: quod fecit Aiod, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Eſt quidem maioris virtutis &amp; animi ſimultatem apertè exercere, palàm in hoſtem reipublicae irruere: ſed non minoris or udentiae, fraudi &amp; inſidijs locum captare, quod ſine motu contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat, minori certè periculo publico atque priuato. <hi>Io. Mariana, de Reg. inſtit. lib. 1. cap. 7.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>That a Tyrant</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>may be killed by open force and armes, whether by violent breaking in
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:19558:26"/>into the Court, or by ioyning of battell, is a matter confeſſed: yea, and by deceit and ambuſhes too, as</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hud <hi>did in killing</hi> Eglon <hi>the King of the Moabites. Indeed it would argue a brauer minde to profeſſe open enmity, and publikely to ruſh in vpon the enemy of the Common-wealth: but it is no leſſe prudence, to take aduantage by fraud and ambuſhes, becauſe it is done without ſtirre, and with leſſe danger ſurely, both pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like and priuate.</hi> His concluſion is, that<note n="h" place="margin">Jn ents vitam graſſari quacun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que arte conceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum; ne cogatur cantùm ſcions aut imprudens ſibi conſcire mor tem. <hi>Id. ibid. in fine.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>it is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to take away his life, by any art whatſoeuer:</hi> with this <hi>prouiſo</hi> onely, <hi>that he be not constrained either wittingly or vnwittingly to bee the cauſe of his owne death.</hi> Where the tenderneſſe of a Ieſuites con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is well worth the obſeruing. Hee maketh no ſcruple at all to take away the mans life: onely hee would aduiſe that hee be not made away, by hauing poyſon conueyed into his meat or drinke, leſt in taking hereof (forſooth) he which is to be killed, ſhould by this meanes haue ſome hand in procuring his owne death.<note n="i" place="margin">Hoc tamen temperamento vti in hâc qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem diſputatio ne licebst, ſi non ipſe qui perimi tur venenum haurire cogitur quo intimis me dullis concepto pereat: ſed ex teriùs ab alio adhibeatur ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bil adiunante co qui perimendus eſt: nimirum cùm tanta vis eſt veneni, vt ſellâ eo aut veſte delibutâ vim interficiendi ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beat. <hi>Id. ibid.</hi>
               </note> Yet poyſon him you may, if you liſt, ſo that the venome be <hi>externally applyed by ſome other, he that is to bee killed helping nothing thereunto: namely, when the force of the poyſon is ſo great, that a ſeat or garment being infected therewith, it may haue ſtrength to kill.</hi> And that ſuch meanes of poyſoning hath been vſed, hee prooueth by diuers practices of the Moores: which we leaue to be conſidered of by <hi>Fitzher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert,</hi> who (to proue that <hi>Squires</hi> intention of poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> in this manner, was but a meere fiction) would perſwade vs that it is not agreeable to the grounds of nature and reaſon,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:19558:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>that any ſuch thing ſhould be.</p>
            <p>Thus we ſee what peſtilent doctrine is daily broched by theſe incendiaries of the world: which, what pernicious effects it hath produced, I need not goe farre to exemplifie; this aſſembly and this place cannot but call to minde the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of that barbarous plot of the Powder-trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. Which being moſt iuſtly charged to haue<note n="k" place="margin">At inquies, omnem modum crudelitatis ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſit ea coniura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio; cum &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, &amp; Regni ordines ſimul implicuiſſet. Id velim ne mire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris. Nam malae &amp; pernitioſae herbae &amp; ſemina conterenda, &amp; radices omnes euellendae ſunt, ne recreſcant. Aliâs etiam, propter paucos ſceleratos, multi ſaepè naufragio pereunt. B. P. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>epiſtolae I. R. impreſſ. anno 1609.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>exceeded all meaſure of cruelty;</hi> as inuoluing not the King alone, but alſo his children, and the States of the Kingdome, and many thouſands of innocent people in the ſame ruine: a wicked varlet (with whoſe name I will not defile this place) ſteppeth forth ſome foure yeeres after, and with a braſen forehead biddeth vs not to wonder at the matter. <hi>For of an euill and pernicious herbe, both the ſeeds are to be cruſhed, and all the roots to be pulled vp, that they grow not againe. And otherwiſe alſo, for a few wicked perſons it falleth out oftentimes that many periſh in ſhipwracke.</hi> In the later of which reaſons we may note theſe mens inſolent impiety toward God: in arrogating vnto themſelues ſuch an abſolute power for the murthering of inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cents, as hee that is Lord of all, hath ouer his owne creatures; the beſt of whom, if he doe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into iudgement with them, will not bee found righteous in his ſight. In the former, we may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue their deadly malice toward Gods Anoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, which they ſufficiently declare will not bee ſatisfied but by the vtter extirpation of him, and all his Royall progenie.</p>
            <p>And whereas for the diſcouery of ſuch wicked
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:19558:27"/>ſpirits, his Maieſty in his Princely wiſedome did cauſe an <hi>Oath of Allegeance</hi> to bee framed; by the tendring whereof he might be the better able to diſtinguiſh betwixt his loyall and diſloyall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, and to put a difference betwixt a ſeditious and a quiet-minded Romaniſt: this companion derideth his ſimplicity, in imagining, that that will ſerue the turne, and ſuppoſing that a Papiſt will thinke himſelfe any whit bound by taking ſuch an oath.<note n="l" place="margin">Sed vide in tantâ aſtutiâ, quanta ſit ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitas. Cùm omnem ſecurita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem in eo iura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento ſibi ſtatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſet; talem ſe modum iura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti, tot cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtantijs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iſſe exiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mabat, qui, ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uâ conſcientiâ, nullâ ratione à quoquam diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ui poſſet. Sed vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere non potuit, ſi pontifex iura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerit, omnes il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius nexus, ſiue de fidelitate Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gi praeſtandâ, ſiue de diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione non ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittendâ, pariter diſſolutos fore. Immo aliud dicam admirabilius. Noſti, credo, iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramentum iniuſtum, ſi tale eſſe euidenter ſciatur, vil apertè declaretur, neminem obligare; ſed ipſo facto nullum eſſe. Regis iuramentum iniuſtum eſſe, ab ipſo Eccleſiae Paſtore ſufficienter declaratum eſt. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ides igitur iam, in ſumum abijſſe illius obligationem; vt vinculum, quod à tot ſapientibus ferreum putabatur, minus ſit, quàm ſtrammeum. <hi>Id. ibid.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>See</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>in ſo great craft, how great ſimplicity doth bewray it ſelfe. When he had pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced all his ſecurity in that oath; hee thought he had found ſuch a manner of oath, knit with ſo many cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, that it could not, with ſafety of conſcience, by any meanes be diſſolued by any man. But hee could not ſee, that if the Pope did diſſolue that oath; all the tyings of it, (whether of performing fidelity to the King, or of admitting no diſpenſation) would bee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued together. Yea, I will ſay another thing that is more admirable. You know (I beleeue) that an vniuſt oath, if it be euidently knowne, or openly declared to be ſuch, bindeth no man; but is voyd</hi> ipſo facto. <hi>That the Kings oath is vniust, hath been ſufficiently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared by the Paſtor of the Church himſelfe. You ſee therefore, that the obligation of it is vaniſhed into ſmoke: ſo that the bond, which by ſo many wiſe men was thought to bee of iron, is become leſſe then of ſtraw.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:19558:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> If matters now be come vnto this paſſe, that ſuch as are addicted to the Pope, will account the Oath of Allegeance to haue leſſe force to binde them then a rope of ſtraw; iudge ye whether y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be not true which hath been ſaid, that in reſpect not of ſpirituall infection onely, but of outward dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger alſo to our State, any Idolaters may be more ſafely permitted then Papiſts. Which I doe not ſpeake, to exaſperate you againſt their perſons, or to ſtirre you vp to make new Lawes for ſhedding of their blood. Their blindneſſe I doe much pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: and my hearts deſire and prayer to God for them is, that they might bee ſaued. Onely this I muſt ſay, that (things ſtanding as they doe) I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not preach peace vnto them.<note place="margin">2. King. 9.22.</note> For as <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaid to <hi>Ioram, What peace, ſo long as the whoredomes of thy Mother Iezabel, and her witchcrafts are ſo many?</hi> ſo muſt I ſay vnto them: What peace can there be, ſo long as you ſuffer your ſelues to bee led by the mother of harlots and abominations of the earth,<note place="margin">Reu. 17.2, 5. and 18.23.</note> who by her ſorceries hath deceiued all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and made them drunke with the wine of her fornication?<note place="margin">Hoſ. 2.2.</note> Let her put away her whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes out of her ſight, and her adulteries from betweene her breaſts; let her repent of her mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and her ſorceries, and her idolatries: or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, becauſe ſhe is paſt all hope, let thoſe that are ſeduced by her, ceaſe to communicate with her in theſe abominable iniquities; and wee ſhall be all ready to meet them, and reioyce with the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels in heauen for their conuerſion. In the meane time, they who ſit at the Helme, and haue the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:19558:28"/>charge of our Church and Common wealth committed to them, muſt prouide by all good meanes, that God bee not diſhonoured by their open Idolatries, nor our King and State indan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gered by their ſecret trecheries. Good Lawes there are already enacted to this purpoſe; which of they were duly put in execution, wee ſhould bane leſſe need to thinke of making new. But it is nor my part to preſſe this poyne. I will there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conclude as I did begin: <hi>I ſpeake as to wiſe men; Iudge ye what I ſay.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2. Tim. 2.7.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> what I ſay, and the Lord giue you vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> all thing.</p>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:19558:28"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
